Contact:

mattia.sensi@inria.fr mattiasensei@gmail.com Personal website

Address:

Via San Pietro 1, 35010 Vigonza (PD) - Italy

Languages:

Italian (C2) English (C1, IELTS 7.5)

Computer softwares:

断_EX Matlab Wolfram Mathematica Python Microsoft Office tools

Mattia Sensi, Ph.D.

Postdoctoral researcher at Inria

About Me

My research interests are primarily mathematical biology and dynamical systems, and the main topic of my research at the moment is mathematical models of neural activity. My major expertise is the analysis of ODE systems evolving on multiple time scale, and mathematical epidemiology. I have worked on the analysis of PDE systems and on models of epidemics on networks. I am an advanced user of Matlab and MTEX, and a competent user of Wolfram Mathematica and Python.

Research experience

• Postdoctoral researcher in Mathematics

MathNeuro, Inria Sophia Antipolis, Biot, France, December 2021 – present. Postdoctoral researcher in the group of Prof. Mathieu Desroches.

• Postdoctoral researcher in Mathematics

NAS, TUDelft, Delft, The Netherlands, March 2021 – November 2021. Postdoctoral researcher in the project "Epidemics over Human Contact Graphs", in the group of Prof. Piet Van Mieghem.

Education

• Ph.D. in Mathematics, cum laude

Università degli Studi di Trento, Trento, Italy, 2017-2021. Title of the thesis: "A Geometric Singular Perturbation approach to epidemic compartmental models", under the supervision of Prof. Andrea Pugliese.

• Master's Degree in Mathematics

Universiteit van Amsterdam, Amsterdam, The Netherlands, 2015–2017. Title of the thesis: "Homoclinic vegetation stripes in a Klausmeier-Gray-Scott model", under the supervision of Prof. Dr. Arjen Doelman.

Bachelor's Degree in Mathematics

Università degli Studi di Padova, Padova, Italy, 2011–2014. Title of the thesis: "Portfolio optimization for quadratic utility function with partial information", under the supervision of Prof. Wolfgang J. Runggaldier.

Articles

- H. Jardón-Kojakhmetov, C. Kuehn, A. Pugliese and M. Sensi. *A geometric analysis of the SIR, SIRS and SIRWS epidemiological models*. Nonlinear Analysis: Real World Applications, Volume 58, April 2021, 103220
- H. Jardón-Kojakhmetov, C. Kuehn, A. Pugliese and M. Sensi. A geometric analysis of the SIRS epidemiological model on a homogeneous network. Journal of Mathematical Biology 83, 37 (2021)
- T. Lorenzi, A. Pugliese, M. Sensi and A. Zardini. Evolutionary dynamics in an SI epidemic model with phenotype-structured susceptible compartment. Journal of Mathematical Biology 83, 72 (2021)
- S. Ottaviano, M. Sensi and S. Sottile. *Global stability of SAIRS epidemic models*. Nonlinear Analysis: Real World Applications, Volume 65, June 2022, 103501
- B. Chang, L. Yang, M. Sensi, M. A. Achterberg, F. Wang, M. Rinaldi and P. Van Mieghem. *Markov Modulated Process to model human mobility*. Complex Networks & Their Applications X. Studies in Computational Intelligence, vol 1015, Springer
- S. Sottile, O. Kahramanogullari and M. Sensi. How network properties and epidemic parameters influence stochastic SIR dynamics on scale-free random networks. Journal of Simulation, Volume 16, Issue 4 (2022)
- N. Cangiotti and M. Sensi. *A geometric characterization of VES and Kadiyala-type production functions*. Filomat, Volume 35, No 5 (2021)

• N. Cangiotti and M. Sensi. Notes on a conformal characterization of 2-dimensional Lorentzian manifolds with constant Ricci scalar curvature. U.P.B. Sci. Bull., Series A, Vol. 83, Iss. 2, 2021

Preprints

- P. Kaklamanos, C. Kuehn, N. Popovic and M. Sensi. Entry-exit functions in fast-slow systems with intersecting eigenvalues. Preprint on arXiv
- S. Ottaviano, M. Sensi and S. Sottile. Global stability of multi-group SAIRS epidemic models. Preprint on arXiv
- M. A. Achterberg and M. Sensi. A minimal model for adaptive SIS epidemics. Preprint on arXiv
- N. Cangiotti, M. Capolli, M. Sensi and S. Sottile. A survey on Lyapunov functions for epidemic compartmental models. Preprint on arXiv
- M. Aguiar, B. Kooi, A. Pugliese, M. Sensi and N. Stollenwerk. Time scale separation in the vector borne disease model SIRUV via center manifold analysis. Preprint on medRxiv
- N. Cangiotti, M. Capolli and M. Sensi. A Generalization of Lanchester's Model of Warfare. Preprint on arXiv

Teaching experience

• At Inria – Université Côte d'Azur:

Teacher of Mathematics for *Linear Algebra Bootcamp*, for first year students of Master's Degree in Computational Neuroscience, September – October 2022

• At Università degli Studi di Trento:

Assistant teacher for Prof. Alberto Valli's course *Analisi 1*, for first year students of Bachelor's Degree in Civil, Environmental and Mechanical Engineering, September 2018 – February 2019, September 2020 – February 2021, September 2022 – December 2022

Tutor for Prof. Andrea Pugliese's course *Probabilità e Statistica 2*, for second year students of Bachelor's Degree in Biotechnologies, February 2018 – May 2018

• At Università Popolare Trentina (CFP-UPT):

Teacher of Mathematics, October 2019 - June 2020

• At Universiteit van Amsterdam:

Assistant teacher for Prof. Dr. Rob Stevenson's course *Numerieke Analyse*, for third year students of Bachelor's Degree in Mathematics, February 2017 – June 2017 Assistant teacher for Dr. Han Peters' course *Wiskunde 3*, for third year students of Bachelor's Degree in Physics, November 2015 – December 2015

Other experiences

Private tutor

Amsterdam and Utrecht, April 2016 – June 2017. Private tutor for WisMon / Bèta onderwijsinstituut

• Freelance private teacher

2008 – present. Freelance private teacher of Mathematics and Physics, for high-school and university students

Mentoring

• Master thesis

Brian Chang, February 2021 – June 2021. Modeling the Spread of Epidemics Liufei Yang, February 2021 – June 2021. Developing a Markov-Modulated Process Model for Mobility Processes

Visiting periods

• Visiting postdoc

Trento, Italy, 5 – 8 December 2022. Visiting postdoc at University of Trento, working with Prof. Andrea Pugliese and Sara Sottile

Visiting postdoc

Amsterdam and Groningen, the Netherlands, 21 – 25 November 2022. Visiting postdoc at VU Amsterdam and Rijksuniversiteit Groningen, working with Prof. Bob Rink and Prof. Hildeberto Jardón-Kojakhmetov

• Visiting PhD student

München, Germany, 15 April – 15 June 2019. Visiting PhD student at Technische Universität München (TUM), working with Prof. Christian Kuehn and Dr. Hildeberto Jardón-Kojakhmetov

Communications

• 7 December 2022, invited speaker

Seminar: Mathematics Seminar, University of Trento Title: "Delayed loss of stability in multiple time scale models of natural phenomena"

• 23 November 2022, invited speaker

Seminar: Floris Takens Seminar, Rijksuniversiteit Groningen Title: "Entry-exit functions in fast-slow systems with intersecting eigenvalues"

• 21 November 2022, invited speaker

Seminar: Extra Dynamics Seminar, VU Amsterdam Title: "A Geometric Singular Perturbation approach to epidemic compartmental models"

• 14 October 2022, invited speaker

Seminar: Applied and Computational Mathematics, University of Edinburgh Title: "Delayed loss of stability in multiple time scale models of natural phenomena"

• 19-23 September 2022, minisymposium organizer and contributed speaker

Conference: ECMTB 2022, Heidelberg

Title: "A generalization of the full SNARE-SM model", part of the minisymposium "Recent advances in mathematical modelling in neuroscience"

• 17-22 July 2022, contributed speaker

Conference: ENOC 2022, Lyon

Title: "Delayed loss of stability in multiple time scale models of natural phenomena", part of the minisymposium "MS-05 Slow-Fast Systems and Phenomena"

• 23-27 May 2022, contributed speaker

Conference: 100 UMI - 800 UniPD, Padova

Title: "A Geometric Singular Perturbation approach to epidemic compartmental models"

• 22 April 2022 – present, organizer

MathNeuro seminars, cycle of seminars on mathematical models in neuroscience

• 11 March 2022, invited speaker

Seminar: Edinburgh Dynamical Systems Study Group, University of Edinburgh Title: "Entry-exit functions: beyond eigenvalue separation"

• 18 June 2021, invited speaker

Seminar: Edinburgh Dynamical Systems Study Group, University of Edinburgh Title: "A Geometric Singular Perturbation approach to epidemic compartmental models"

• 4–7 February 2020, organizer, scientific committee and contributed speaker

Conference: DSABNS 2020, Trento

Title: "A GSPT approach to epidemics on homogeneous graphs"

• 12 September 2019, invited speaker

Seminar: Doc in Progress, Università degli Studi di Trento Title: "An introduction to Geometric Singular Perturbation Theory"

• 4-5 July 2019, contributed speaker

Workshop: Edinburgh Slow-Fast-Ival, Edinburgh

Title: "A GSPT approach to perturbed SIR and SIRWS models"

• 3-6 February 2019, contributed speaker

Conference: DSABNS 2019, Naples

Title: "A GSPT approach to perturbed SIR and SIRWS models"

• 21 January 2019, invited speaker

Seminar: Oberseminar Dynamics, TUM Munich

Title: "A GSPT approach to perturbed SIR and SIRWS models"

Reviewing

Journals

Journal of Mathematical Biology

Advances in Difference Equations

Mathematical Methods in the Applied Sciences

Journal of Complex Networks

Mathematical Biosciences and Engineering

Journal of Biological Systems

International Journal of Biomathematics

Mathematics and Computers in Simulation

Attended Conferences & Workshops

• 30 June – 1 July 2022, selected participant

Workshop: NeuroMod Meeting 2022, Antibes

• 6-9 September 2021, selected participant

Online workshop: MoDiS – Modelling Diffusive Systems: Theory & Biological Applications, Edinburgh

• 12–15 April 2021, selected participant

Online Hausdorff School: Diffusive Systems, Bonn

• 1-8 September 2019, selected participant

Summer school: Mathematical Biology on the Mediterranean Conference, Samos

• 22–26 July 2019, selected participant

Summer school: Multiscale Phenomena in Geometry and Dynamics, München

• 8-11 October 2018, selected participant

Workshop: Mathematics for BioMedicine, Rome

• 19-26 August 2018, selected participant

Summer school: The Helsinki Summer School on Mathematical Ecology and Evolution 2018, Turku

Membership

• 2017-2021, GNAMPA - INdAM

Member of the group *Gruppo Nazionale per l'Analisi Matematica*, la Probabilità e le loro Applicazioni, of the Istituto Nazionale di Alta Matematica